上一个视频我们从原恒星的例子中发现了一个格式字符串漏洞，
but had it compiled on a modern system with ASLR and 64bit.
一开始我以为我们解不出来，但还是摸索了一些窍门，四处游玩。
with it, but then actually figured out a reliable technique.
So let’s explore some more of the format levels.
Format1, at first, looks very simple.
记得上一次我们失败是因为它要求我们写精确的目标
value 0xdeadbeef, and here we just have to write..
什么？
Let’s have quick look if our trick still works.
So this level also takes an argument, but passes it directly to printf.
No sprintf and buffer involved.
Anyway.
we compile it again on our 64bit ubuntu version and open it in gdb.
然后，我们在目标的if比较处设置了一个断点，运行它，并使用它作为参数
AAAAAAAAAA.
Then we have a look at the stack.
看到我们的as怎么不出现了吗？
他们在哪里？
Let’s keep looking further down.
Oh wow.
They are all the way down there.
又是什么东西？
Well so.
看，我们没有把字符串输入复制到一个局部变量上，就像上一个缓冲区一样。
challenge.
We directly print the arguments.
参数和环境变量一起放在开始处。
of the stack.
So these are the environment variables.
你看，没有堆栈地址我们可以像上次那样重写和滥用
level.
That sucks.
But actually it’s still solveable, we don’t need the trick from last video at all.
It’s simpler than you might think.
但是让我们来探讨下一个挑战，格式2，我们还没有看到的那个
and boils down to the same thing.
看起来更有希望，对吧？
It does read data into a local variable on the stack.
But it doesn’t look like we can overflow the buffer.
This program gets the input from standard input instead of an argument.
然后检查目标是否
64.
Ok.
So let’s compile it and open it in gdb.
Again we look for the if-compare, seems to be here, 0x40 is 64.
And set a breakpoint then run it.
This time it’s waiting for input, so enter some As and Bs.
Now we hit the breakpoint and let’s have a look at the stack.
mh，我们知道我们的缓冲区有512个字节，看起来有一堆地址。
in range.
但为什么呢，512字节的缓冲区不是未分配的还是空的？
Well no not really.
您可以看到它是堆栈上的一个局部变量，这意味着它只是移动了堆栈指针。
further up to make space for it, but doesn’t clear it.
所以这些是以前运行的，在那里有一个堆栈的其他函数的剩余值，
then got destroyed again when they returned, but their values always remain there.
对于正常的程序执行来说，这并不重要，除非您不能期望
一个用零初始化的变量，因为你可能运气不好，而且有东西在里面。
it’s place before.
Anyway.
Let’s see where our target variable is.
我们可以先用印刷体，然后用安培标靶得到一个指针，所以基本上地址
of target.
但那是什么？
看起来不像堆栈地址？
Somebody who has some experience with exploitation on 64bit knows already what that is.
It’s a very recognisable address.
使用vmmap，您可以检查虚拟内存，并查看它是否是二进制文件的一部分？
Look at the permissions for this memory region.
It is read and writeable, not executable.
So it’s not where code is.
It’s in a data segment.
And when we look at the code we see that target isn’t defined in a function as local variable.
It’s a global variable, so it’s placed in a data segment.
现在，如果您对64位目标的开发有一些经验，您也知道这意味着，
this address is not affected by ASLR by default.
Lets add another printf here, like we did last video to print the address of target.
And when we run it a few times, you see target doesn’t change.
令人惊叹的！
So it should be fairly straight forward.
Step 1: let’s find our input on the stack.
We enter some As followed by %x to print stack values.
And here we are.
1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6.
At offset 6 we have our input.
所以我们可以把地址放在那里而不是as，然后用6%x替换
the %n to write to it.
Let’s try it.
So we should now enter our input via echo, so we can encode raw characters in hex.
Then pipe the input into format2.
So let’s enter the address of target.
Ah see, there it is, but it’s 4 bytes, so there is also a space still included.
This has to be a zero, because the address is only 3 bytes.
So we add that, but now we don’t see any output anymore.
怎么搞的？
Well, printf prints strings.
And strings are null-terminated in C. So printf stops when it reahed the 0.
So we never reach our %x format modifiers.
This means, we should move our address to the end, so we can have format stuff before.
Now let’s try to find again our address.
This time I’m using the dollar syntax to enter an offset directly.
So we know our start was at offset 6, so the address has to be further down.
别忘了在命令行上逃离美元，因为美元是特别的
charachter for the shell.
If we keep going with the offsets, we can find the As.
现在，有时偏移量可能不正确，所以可能需要添加或删除一些字符
as padding to align it perfectly.
Ok now looks good.
Let’s change it to a %n.
Segmentation fault.
Well that didn’t work.
Weird.
让我们将输入写入一个文件，打开gdb，并使用该文件作为输入进行调查
the crash.
So here we are at a move.
It tries to move whatever is in r15d into the address in rax.
And so rax appears to be an invalid address.
It’s not our target.
There is a 0xa.
And that is obviously a newline.
So that’s the issue.
We are on 64bit, so we have 64bit addresses.
But we only entered 4 bytes, and after the echo is a newline.
So we just have to add 4 more nullbytes.
Ok we don’t get a crash now.
But target is still 0.
这是怎么回事？
Let’s make it crash again by making the address invalid again.
这样我们就可以调查我们的地址是否正确以及
written to it.
So we see, rax looks good.
It only is invalid because of what we changed.
Otherwise it would be great.
所以它试图写R15d，也就是说，0？
什么？
%n不应该写已经打印的字符数吗？
Let’s think for a second.
Ohhhhhh.
Of course it’s 0.
Because we didn’t pint anything yet.
Before we do the %n we obviously have to print something first.
So let’s add %64d, to print 64 characters.
现在有4个字符长，这意味着我们将所有内容都移动了4个，为了
重新对齐所有内容，地址在正确的偏移量，我们必须减去
4 characters somewhere.
But luckily we made the padding earlier large enough and so that’s simple.
And here we go, it’s “you modified the target”.
最后，我们设法利用现代系统的一个简单例子
much hassle.
Goddamit.
So maybe now you wonder, but the system has ASLR, why is this address fixed.
嗯，系统有aslr，像libc这样的系统库受aslr的影响，
您可以看到，当使用ldd打印二进制文件的库依赖项时，
keeps changing.
But the binary itself is not affected by ASLR.
Unless we specifically compile it to be position independent code.
而wie可以使用位置无关的可执行文件和-fpic的-pie标志来实现这一点。
for position independent code.
如果我们现在执行format2并检查目标的地址，那么我们会看到它不断地更改
lot.
Now it’s going to be much harder.
Maybe with some strategies from the last video it’s doable.
I leave that as an exercise to you watching.